<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: personal, | Jeff Richardson]]></title>
  <link href="http://jeffawesome.com/blog/categories/personal/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jeffawesome.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-11-28T02:50:44-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://jeffawesome.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jeff Richardson]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[jeff@masterpieceinteractive.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why I left my web engineer job in San Francisco]]></title>
    <link href="http://jeffawesome.com/blog/2013/11/28/why-i-left-my-web-development-job-in-san-francisco/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-28T02:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://jeffawesome.com/blog/2013/11/28/why-i-left-my-web-development-job-in-san-francisco</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I was in <strong>Silicon Valley</strong>. I had worked for 5 years before I made my way out to the mecca of the tech world.
I remember at one point thinking, this is it. This is the big leagues. I was happy.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>I would like to start out by saying this is not in any attempt to shed a negative light on my previous employer. My goal
is just to express my feelings that led me to leave the company.</p>

<p>I was the Sr Web Engineer  at a San Francisco tech company, how many people can say that? I made friends with the people on my
team I really enjoyed joking around and just working with them.</p>

<p>We had hectic deadlines, but I love what I do and that's never stopped me before. My wife was pregnant at the time and
decided to stay in Oklahoma with her family to help with the pregnancy. She flew in on a thursday one evening. I remember having
a late meeting and it ruining our plans that night, but that was okay because I was just glad to have her around the few days... and that's not
at all one of the reasons I left. <strong> I love crazy intense deadlines </strong>. There is something very rewarding about being overworked for
a week or two and then completing a pretty complex problem.</p>

<p>I remember being very happy and then I noticed things changing. A lot of our work was being sent overseas. We were mainly in charge
of making sure the overseas team did things right, QA without any development. That was very new to me. I didn't come to San Francisco
to throw in the towel as a web developer. I came there because this was supposed to be the place where I would grow exponentially, work
on amazing products, and solve real world problems.</p>

<p>Before I go on I would like to note something...I didn't go to college, I made the decision not to after I got hired on as a Full time
salaried web developer literally a week after my high school graduation. I talked with one of my most influential teachers at the time
and she told me that if I had the opportunity to make almost the same as her right out of high school that I should take it... so I did.
I don't regret it. I love learning. I have an obsession with it... and its not just about learning things about computers. One of my
biggest interests is The Brain and behavior and learning. A lot of that has to do with my aunt and my mother. They are both psychologists
and I grew up listening to them talk about famous experiments and theories. I also feel that paying $20,000 a semester to
<strong> learn/be talked to about </strong> things I am not passionate about is a waste of money... but society thinks otherwise... but that is
for another day.</p>

<p>I was one day while at the company told in a pretty condescending way It was inspiring to see how I didn't even go to college. I'm
still not 100% sure what that meant, maybe it wasn't condescending and i'm sensitive about it or something, but I don't think so. There
are some things I know I missed out on, but overall I don't think i'll ever regret not going to college... and I know I never
want to work on a government site (which requires a degree)... those things are turning out great and don't need me ;).</p>

<p>The biggest reason I decided to move was because as an Engineer it is my duty to always learn and always expand my knowledge. That
wasn't happening with the company I was working for at the time. I read a really interesting article a few weeks before I finally gave my notice, about how the really talented developers
will leave a company if they aren't going to learn. I like to think of myself as a talented developer and that was it. I made up my mind.
I was going to put in my notice. I took a week off to think things over, especially with a kiddo about to be born, giving up
a San Francisco Front End Engineer salary isn't always an easy decision.</p>

<p>I'm now working as a Full Stack Engineer in Oklahoma and even though the city isn't the mecca of development I am very happy. On any
given day I could be working on server side architecture, client side, or just recently native application development.
I've grown more in the past 6 months then I have since I first started back in 2008.</p>

<p>I was told by a friend I worked with at my previous employer.. "You can't just leave when you're unhappy with a job, there will be
other jobs in San Francisco that you won't be happy with, you just cant leave those." My reply is that while traditionally this might
have been true, for web developers, for us... we can leave. I firmly believe that as Web Developers we are in a very
interesting position. We hold an extremely valuable skill. We can build almost anything in the world and that's needed. If you don't
believe in what you're building, what is the point? Why are you doing this? Why are you working at your current job. I'm not advocating
leaving a job right away, talk with management you might find you don't have to leave the company to be happy, for me it was the only
logical choice. I believe that if you can... only apply at companies that deal with something you are passionate about otherwise
in this exciting field we are no different then the guy working the 9 - 5 at the bank not because he loves it but because its a
paycheck. And I will glady take a $30,000 + pay decrease to do something interesting then be miserable simply for money. Thats why I left
my job in San Francisco.</p>

<p>Be Awesome
Jeff Richardson :)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
