<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: thoughts | Jeff Richardson]]></title>
  <link href="http://jeffawesome.com/blog/categories/thoughts/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jeffawesome.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-11-28T02:52:36-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://jeffawesome.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jeff Richardson]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[jeff@masterpieceinteractive.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Learning on the fly]]></title>
    <link href="http://jeffawesome.com/blog/2013/07/31/learning-on-the-fly/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-31T23:22:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jeffawesome.com/blog/2013/07/31/learning-on-the-fly</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I've made a dramatic change in my career over the past few months. I went from completely front end development to a focus on the full stack.
Throughout my career I have always dabbled a bit in the backend changing a few lines of codes in php and then uploading them to the server via ssh or ftp, but
this is a whole new ball game. Each day I experiment and learn something new. Its 100% frustrating but get this <strong> I love it </strong>.</p>

<p>I've been working as a web developer professionally since 2008, I was 19 then, and i'm 24 now. One thing I experienced that first year and a half of my
career was this extreme learning growth spurt. I remember being completely lost but eventually I would figure it out. It wasn't always easy,
I had to develop with ie 6 compatability in mind, but at the end of the day I would always have a sense of accomplishment. I don't want anyone to
think I stumbled upon this field with no knowledge I had a fundamental understanding of html and css and layouts back then before jumping in,
but it wasn't until I jumped into developing site after site that I really started to exercise this knowledge and put it to the test.</p>

<p>Fast forward to today. I've been working as a full stack developer and I feel I'm back at the beginning of the learning cycle, but I think as developers
maybe that's the most appropriate place for us to be. I speak from experience when I say its extermely easy to get stuck in this idea of a label. Were
a front end developer, or a designer, or a programmer. It takes a large amount of work and dedication to learning something new and its extremely
frustrating at first, and maybe always.. isn't our job about solving problems... some we've never had to solve before, but eventually things get easier
and you start to grasp ideas you thought you were never going to grasp. Its a wonderful feeling to finally understand, and use , an idea that you've
been trying to grasp for a while.</p>

<p>I know this idea of always learning isn't new at all, but its something I truly believe in. We don't have to be the best or the smartest but if we
always strive to learn and improve I really think we'll always have a job... an increasingly complex job at that. I think about a quote I heard first from a pretty
cool guy <a href="http://okdork.com/">Noah Kagen</a> "If its uncomfortable, you're growing.". I can't tell you how often I think about that quote,
especially when learning what at first feels awkward like learning vim, using the terminal for everything, or learning ruby and then rails within a month
period... but its extremely true. Each day things feel less awkward, but its only because I'm learning and its the normal progression. I can't wait
to get a bit more awkward just when I think I've learned it all :).</p>

<p>Be Awesome</p>

<p>Jeff Richardson</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
